# JAYLEN WANG

Carnegie Mellon University Email: jaylenw@andrew.cmu.edu

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering Web: https://jaylenwang7.github.io

## **BRIEF BIOGRAPHY**

My work bridges computer architecture and software systems, demonstrating the importance of that bridge in enabling sustainable data center systems via solutions that span the compute stack.

As the demand for web services continues to grow, data centers are scaling up to meet the demand, consuming a massive amount of energy and producing significant carbon emissions. My research focuses on addressing the growing carbon emissions, produced both by running and manufacturing hardware, of data centers by analyzing inefficiencies across computer architecture and software systems and designing solutions to make these systems more energy and carbon efficient.

My work is one of the first to examine the environmental impact of hyperscale web systems and to provide actionable insights to reduce it. My work integrates carbon efficiency into computer system design, as it is crucial for sustainable growth and access to critical web services in both developed and developing nations. My work is a step towards curbing computing's contributions towards climate change and promoting sustainable computing practices.

My research has been recognized with the NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program (GRFP) Award and the 2023 Benjamin Garver Lamme/Westinghouse Graduate Fellowship.

## **EDUCATION**

# Ph.D., Electrical and Computer Engineering

Carnegie Mellon University Aug 2022 - Present

Advisor: Prof. Akshitha Sriraman

NSF GRFP Fellow

Dissertation Title: Enabling Sustainable Web Systems

## B.Sc., Electrical Engineering

PIs: Profs. David Brooks & Gu-Yeon Wei

Minor in Computer Science

GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0; Member of Phi Beta Kappa

Harvard University

Aug 2018 - May 2022

#### PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE AND JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Jaylen Wang, Daniel S. Berger, Fiodar Kazhamiaka, Celine Irvene, Chaojie Zhang, Esha Choukse, Kali Frost, Rodrigo Fonseca, Brijesh Warrier, Chetan Bansal, Jonathan Stern, Ricardo Bianchini, and Akshitha Sriraman. Designing Cloud Servers for Lower Carbon. 51st International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA 2024). June 2024.

## AWARDS AND HONORS

Jack and Mildred Bowers Scholarship in Engineering Full tuition support for third year of PhD	2024
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program (GRFP) Award Winner Awarded \$171,000 as part of prestigious fellowship supporting exceptional graduate students in STEM	2023
Ford Foundation 2023 Predoctoral Fellowship Competition Honorable Mention Honorable mention given to top Ford Fellowship candidates	2023
Benjamin Garver Lamme/Westinghouse Graduate Fellowship Full tuition support for second year of PhD	2023
Carnegie Institute of Technology Dean's Fellow Awarded \$83,000 towards tuition, stipend, and travel	2022
Harvard SEAS Dean's Engineering Design Award	2022

Awarded \$500 for having one of the top 7 (out of 43) best Senior engineering design projects

Sophia Freund Prize Awarded \$1000 as highest ranking undergraduate in the Electrical Engineering department	2022
Phi Beta Kappa Member Admitted into Harvard's chapter, one of 146 out of 1962 (7.4%) students	2022
Derek Bok Center Distinction in Teaching Awarded to most highly rated (by students) TAs; received distinction in three semesters	2020, 2021
John Harvard Scholar Award given to top 5% (4.0 GPA) of students in respective class	2020
Harvard College Research Program Funding Recipient Awarded \$3,500 to perform independent research during the summer	2019
Detur Prize Winner Recognizes students with top academic standing in their first year at Harvard	2019

#### PEER-REVIEWED WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

- Jaylen Wang, Melissa Pan, Udit Gupta, and Akshitha Sriraman. Giving Old Servers New Life at Hyper-scale. 6th Young Architect Workshop (YArch 2024) held in conjunction with ASPLOS. June 2024.

Performs the first ever characterization of server generations for microservice-based web services to enable hardware lifetime extension

- Jialun Lyu, Jaylen Wang, Kali Frost, Chaojie Zhang, Celine Irvene, Esha Choukse, Rodrigo Fonseca, Ricardo Bianchini, Fiodar Kazhamiaka, and Daniel S. Berger. Myths and Misconceptions Around Reducing Embedded Carbon for Cloud Platforms. 2nd Workshop on Sustainable Computer Systems (HotCarbon 2023). July 2023.
- Jaylen Wang, Udit Gupta, and Akshitha Sriraman. Giving Old Servers New Life at Hyperscale. 1st
   Workshop on Hot Topics in System Infrastructure (HotInfra 2023) held in conjunction with ISCA. June 2023.

Introduces equity as a first-order design metric in modern data center scheduling systems

Jaylen Wang, Abdulrahman Mahmoud, Gu-Yeon Wei, and David Brooks. A Dataflow-Aware Fault Resilience Analysis Framework for Deep Neural Network Accelerators. 4th Young Architect Workshop (YArch 2021) held in conjunction with ASPLOS. March 2022.

Introduces a new framework and tool to quickly and accurately assess the reliability of deep neural network accelerator designs to random bit flips, providing insights for resilient accelerator design

#### INVITED SEMINAR TALKS

#### Designing Cloud Servers for Lower Carbon

– Google SystemsResearch@Google (SRG) Group	September 2024
– University of California San Diego	April 2024
– University of California Riverside	April 2024
– University of Southern California	$April\ 2024$
- University of California Los Angeles	$April\ 2024$

## PROFESSIONAL SERVICE/IMPACT

- Graduate Student Panelist for Undergrad Architecture Mentoring Workshop (uArch) held in conjunction with ISCA. Jun 2024
- Artifact Evaluation Committee Member for International Symposium on Microarchitecture 2024 (MICRO 2024).
   Nov 2024.
- (Organized Workshop) Jaylen Wang, Sara Mahdizadeh Shahri, and Akshitha Sriraman. 1st Workshop on Hot Topics in Ethical Computer Systems (HotEthics 2024) held in conjunction with ASPLOS. Apr 2024.
  - Developed, advertised, organized, and reviewed papers for the 1st Workshop on Hot Topics in Ethical Computer Systems.
- Co-Author in ACM SIGARCH Computer Architecture Today blog article Reducing Embodied Carbon is Important (ACM SIGARCH 2023). Aug 2023. ⊕
- Artifact Evaluation Committee Member for Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems 2024 (ASPLOS 2023). Oct 2023.

Organized and moderated the first panel on sustainable systems research at HotOS with five expert panelists in the field.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# IBM Research Intern, IBM Research, Yorktown Heights, NY

May 2024 - August 2024

Mentor: Asser Tantawi

Developing new frameworks and strategies for more sustainable cross-cluster batch job scheduling.

# Azure Systems Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA

May 2023 - August 2023

Mentor: Fiodar Kazhamiaka

Developing a framework based on an understanding of server design's data center-scale impact to improve Azure's resource and carbon efficiency.

# Graduate Research Assistant, Carnegie Mellon University

Aug 2022 - Present

Advisor: Prof. Akshitha Sriraman

Introducing sustainability as a first-order hardware/software system design metric for hyperscale systems and redesigning data center systems to promote hardware reuse

#### Undergraduate Research Assistant, Harvard University

March 2021 - Aug 2022

Lab: Harvard Architecture, Circuits, and Compilers Group

Advisors: Dr. Abdulrahman Mahmoud, Profs. Gu-Yeon Wei and David Brooks

Developing a hardware-aware framework for analyzing the resilience of deep neural network accelerators to soft errors, considering the reuse of values in an accelerator's dataflow propagation

# Engineering Development Group Intern, MathWorks

May 2021 - Aug 2021

Team: Deep Learning HDL Toolbox Supervisors: Wang Chen, Siyuan Xu

Enabling efficient mapping of non-square convolution kernels onto square processing-element arrays, allowing users to deploy models using non-square kernels onto FPGAs

# Undergraduate Research Assistant, Harvard University

May 2020 - Aug 2020

Lab: Harvard Edge Computing Lab Advisor: Prof. Vijay Janapa Reddi

Analyzing how using SLAM for localization affects efficiency and power usage within autonomous drone applications by integrating SLAM algorithms into an open-sourced drone benchmarking framework

# Undergraduate Research Assistant, Harvard University

May 2019 - Aug 2019

Fall 2019

Lab: Hoffman Physics Lab Advisor: Prof. Jenny Hoffman

Developing a tensioning system for an XY-walker system to extend the range of a scanning tunneling microscope used to research the proximity effect of superconductivity

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# Undergraduate Teaching Assistant, Harvard University

- Integration, Series and Differential Equations; Dr. Hakim Walker

– Systems Programming and Machine Organization; Prof. Eddie Kohler	Fall 2020, 2021
– Circuits, Devices, and Transduction; Profs. Gage Hills & Woodward Yang	Fall 2021
– Systems and Control; Profs. Li Na & Yue Lu	Fall 2021
– Introduction to Electrical Engineering; Profs. Chris Lombardo & Marko Loncar	Spring 2021

# LEADERSHIP & VOLUNTEERING

– CMU Institute of Technology K-12 Outreach, STEM Volunteer	$2023 ext{-}Present$
– President of Harvard Club Tennis	2019-2022
– President of Harvard College Engineering Society	2020-2021
- Co-President of Harvard Engineering Peer Concentration Advisors	2020-2021

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages	C/C++, Python, Shell, Verilog, x86 Assembly
System Skills	Low-level Systems Programming, Performance Characterization,
Tools and Frameworks	Scripting, Docker Pin, gem5, Linux perf, Intel PMU tools, PyTorch, Catapult HLS, Git

#### REFERENCES

- 1. Prof. Akshitha Sriraman (akshitha@cmu.edu) Assistant Professor, Carnegie Mellon University
- 2. Daniel S. Berger (daberg@microsoft.com) Researcher in Azure Systems Research Group, Microsoft
- 3. Fiodar Kazhamiaka (fkazhamiaka@microsoft.com) Researcher in Azure Systems Research Group, Microsoft
- 4. Prof. David Brooks (dbrooks@g.harvard.edu) Haley Family Professor of Computer Science, Harvard University
- 5. Prof. Udit Gupta (ugupta@cornell.edu) Assistant Professor, Cornell University